Guide to the Wolf Franck collection
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Wolf Franck collection
1816-1971
Franck, Wolf. Collector
.5 linear ft. (1 half sized document box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1605
9313625
Biographical Note
Wolf Franck was a German scholar and radio broadcaster who relocated to New York during World War II. Franck was a radio broadcaster in Berlin, but moved to Paris in 1933 after Hitler came to power in Germany. He wrote several books, including one on exiles, and many articles, and associated with Andre Gide, Thomas and Heinrich Mann, Berthold Brecht, among others. In June 1940, when the Germans began their occupation of Paris, he was captured, sent to a French concentration camp but escaped and ended up in Casablanca. President Franklin Roosevelt gave Wolf Franck a personal visa to emigrate to the United States in 1941. Wolf Franck met his future wife Jane Franck while at Columbia University and they married in 1953.
Scope and Content
The collection includes both Wolf Franck's autograph collection, as well as some correspondence between Franck and his wife and notable figures.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 2 series
Series I: Autographs and Ephemera, 1816-1900
Series II: Correspondence, 1941-1973
Subjects
Hegel, Georg Wilhelm Friedrich, 1770-1831.; Correspondence.; Postcards.; Photographs
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least two business days in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Jane Franck Gift 2000
- Series I: Autographs and Ephemera, 1816-1900
  - Autographed Photographs (Box 1)
    - Unidentified (Box 1)
    - Albert Basserman (Box 1)
    - Madame Charles Cahier (Box 1)
    - Max Pallenberg (Box 1)
    - Leopold Reidemeister (Box 1)
    - Ludwig Wüllner (Box 1)
  - Autographed Letters
    - Unidentified to Gabler, 1821 (Box 1)
    - Becker to Prof. Dr. Götz, 1874 (Box 1)
    - Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel, 1816, 1827, 1830 (3 letters) (Box 1)
    - A. Sheldon to Gen. James P. Weston, 1863 (Box 1)
    - Max [Vallenz] to D. Landsberg, 1900 (Box 1)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1941-1973
  - Ida Cassote to W. Franck, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Theo Feldman to Mr. and Mrs. Wolf Franck, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Karl Jaspers to Marga Franck, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Heinrich Mann to Franck, 1941 (Box 1)
  - O. Meyerhof to Franck, 1973 (Box 1)